when is the right time to go into
Solitude you know kind of thing and I
think it's the same for whether you're a
lay person or a monk you have to be able to
person or a monk you have to be able to
be
a you could say a friend to yourself in
a way you have to be able
to uh live with yourself in ease with
ease so you have to be virtuous and
sense restraint and not have this uh a
mind full of Desire fire and hatred and
confusion because if you have that which
is basically have being living with an
enemy if you if you have that kind of
mind which is your enemy and you go and
stay in solitude well you are going to
have a a difficult time so you have to
have a mind which is your
friend and and
and and
any so mind with any of the qualities
that uh a friend would have that you
would consider someone who would be
friend you know kind compassionate
not desirous lustful averse complaining
all the time um anxious and so
on so how do you how do you develop that
friendly mind towards yourself well you
got to to quite a degree uh bring those
lust aversion and distraction confusion
you have to bring that to an end by
being virtuous you know no longer doing things
virtuous you know no longer doing things
you know that are bad for
you bad for your
mind which uh make the Mind lustful and
so on is your actions what if what if
somebody can't help but breaking the
keep breaking the precepts and losing
sensitive
strength that's that's going to happen
anyway so everybody's going to like you
know not be able to help themselves in
the beginning but with you just keep
trying and and seeing and seeing the
benefit of trying and getting stronger
and stronger and eventually you break
them less and less so to speak could
that could that person still go into
seclusion they're trying their best but
you know failing every now and then oh
yeah to to the degree that they are not
that lustful that full of hate and that
full of confusion yeah then I think you
know seclusion is good for you know just
looking at the Mind reflecting on the
the suitors reflecting on these
subjects a a a quiet time not intense
seclusion but a quiet time in of the day
um a space where you can retire to is
good for any philosopher any anyone who
wants to heal their mind needs to meet
that mind and the best place for meeting
it is a place
of where there's no
business no others
around when forests go for a walk even a
long long walk already a person who's
you know just living a normal lay life
if they just go on the weekend to a
forest that already is by themselves
contempt you start to think about your life what
you start to think about your life what
what you're going to do you know with
your life all the things that happen you
start rehashing the past
and just just by that person can see
that just walking alone in the forest
you can already see how you start going
inwards and looking at yourself and
that's another thing if you
can't face yourself if you can't even
just admit to the things that you did
wrong in the past that walk you won't
even be going to that forest for a walk
on the weekend it's just too much you
would have to have your friends with you
you would have to have your music
playing in your ear because you just
can't handle yourself and that that type
of person they need to do a lot more
work actually